Predication is another way that we can
try to deal with control hazards. Unlike
branch prediction when we are really
trying to guess which way the if then
else or a loop or something branch will
be going. Predication is another way for
dealing with control dependencies.
Branch fiction is about guessing where
the program is going. Usually there is
no penalty for being correct in branch
fiction. Pretty much we just keep
fetching as if the branch wasn't even
there. Even if the branch is actually
taken, we can just keep fetching from
the right place and thus avoid any
penalty. But the problem with branch
fiction is that in modern processors,
there is a huge penalty if we are wrong
in predicting. Keep in mind that modern
processors have a deep pipe with lots of
stages before the one in which we figure
out the misprediction. And in each
stage, we have a number of instructions
that we have been doing.
So a misprediction results in throwing
away all of that work. Usually at least
several tens of instructions worth of
work. So the penalty is usually zero
instructions here. And if we have
something like maybe a 12 stage pipeline
with four instructions per
cycle, we're talking about something
like 48 possibly instructions or so. So
let's say about 50 instructions worth of
work wasted. Predication is about doing
work of the both of the directions. So
we basically do the work of both a taken
and not taken direction for a branch.
That way the waste is up to 50% of the
work we've been doing because at the
position where the branch was supposed
to be about half of the stuff we've been
fetching could have been from one path
half of the stuff was from the other and
only half of that work will actually be
used the rest will be thrown away and
then we simply throw away the work from
the wrong path. So what is good about
this? It seems like here if we are
correct we lose nothing. If we are wrong
we lose a lot but we can have very
accurate
prediction. Well here either way we lose
quite a bit. Well let's see how the
branch fiction and something like
predication compare on different types
of conditional branches that we might
want to predict. For a loop usually we
want to do branch fiction. loop
branches the more iterations we have the
more they are
predictable. Whereas with predication in
each iteration of the loop we will be
dividing our work into two. One is do
the next iteration the other one is do
the work after the loop. So if we have a
thousand iterations very little of the
work will end up being done correctly.
Simply the branch is diverging too much.
When we need to decide whether to stay
in the loop or not, we would be starting
the work of both of these. One path goes
after the loop, the other one goes back
into the loop. And then here we have a
decision again to follow that path or
stay in the loop, that path, stay in the
loop. So after a while if we're still
doing the work of all of these parts
concurrently a very small fraction of
the work we are doing ends up being the
staying in the loop work and a lot of it
has to do with various varants of
exiting the loop in each iteration. So
for a loop we want to predict function
call returns same thing except
predication really makes no sense
because calls and returns always go
there. So somehow the direction of not
going there makes no sense to do. So we
want to
predict. Let's say now we have a large
if then else. So what happens? We have a
decision and based on it we do
this or we do
this. Now the question is should we try
to predict this decision or predicate so
that we are doing the work of both and
eventually they will merge and we
continue. And the answer here is that if
we predict we waste up to 50
instructions more likely we waste
nothing. If we predicate and these
branches have equal weight then let's
say we have a 100 instructions here and
100 instructions here. We will execute
200 instructions waste 100 of them
either way. So somehow the amount of
waste with predication
here is larger than even the penalty of
branch misprediction. Pretty much if we
predict and we are right we lose
nothing. If we predict and we are wrong
we lose 50 instructions. Here we lose
100 instructions and we cannot be wrong
or right but either way we are losing
100 instructions. So for a large if then
else it seems like we should be
predicting but let's see how things look
like for a small if then else. Let's say
that we have a decision to make and
depending on the decision we have the
then or the else path but let's say each
is now something like five instructions
long. Now it becomes interesting if we
do predication we will be executing 10
instructions here followed by
instructions that we would do anyway. So
the waste is five instructions either
way. Here we are predicting and if we
are right we waste nothing but if we are
wrong we waste 50 instructions. So our
comparison is that 100% of the time we
waste five instructions with
predication. So we end up with five on
average per instance of this. Whereas
here our branch prediction rate
determines how often we waste this 50.
So it's going to
be let's say
0 10 because it's 10% probability of
mispredicting in which case we end up at
52. So if our accuracy of prediction is
90% or better then in this case we are
better off predicting the branch. But if
our accuracy is less than 90%, we are
better off
predicating. If the if then else is even
smaller, then it biases things more in
favor of predication and less in favor
of branch prediction. So for really
small if than else's, we want to
predicate unless we are reasonably sure
that our branch prediction is going to
be highly accurate.